A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential, Series M FA349
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential, Series M
1977-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Morrow, Hugh
FA349
1.88 Cubic Feet 4 legal document boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 M
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The series is arranged chronologically by date of the speech.
Scope and Contents note
This speech file was maintained by Hugh Morrow, Nelson Rockefeller's press secretary. Mr. Morrow was a speech writer for Mr. Rockefeller during his first term as Governor of New York and became his press secretary beginning with his second term in 1963. Mr. Morrow served Mr. Rockefeller throughout his term as Vice President and during his years as a private citizen before and after the Vice Presidency.
This collection of speeches and press releases reflects Rockefeller's transition from public official to a private citizen and offers some insight to his public activities during the last two years of his life. Mr. Rockefeller maintained his reputation as a knowledgeable and outspoken observer of politics and foreign affairs by accepting invitations to speak before political, civic, and private groups. He addressed issues such as the energy crisis, Soviet expansion, national security, and peace in the Middle East. After returning to private life, Mr. Rockefeller also indulged his passion for art by establishing two related businesses: an art reproduction company called the Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. (NRC) and an art book publishing business called Nelson Rockefeller Publications, Inc. This series includes press releases announcing the establishment and development of these two ventures. At Mr. Morrow's suggestion, Nelson Rockefeller began to cultivate a public image as an art dealer and art expert by accepting invitations to give lectures on art. Transcripts for two such lectures, on December 16, 1977, and November 15, 1978, are included. There is also a tape recording of the first one.
This series begins with files of some public remarks Mr. Rockefeller made during the last days of the Ford Administration in January 1977 and concludes with press releases on the memorial services after Rockefeller's death on January 26, 1979. The speech files contain one or more of four different versions of each speech: draft, reading copy, transcript, or press release. The folder descriptions list which versions exist for each speech. Drafts and reading copies are likely to include Mr. Rockefeller's handwritten changes and notations. A transcript is a verbatim record of the remarks. For each speech, Mr. Morrow's office usually issued a press release containing excerpts of Mr. Rockefeller's remarks. Some files contain correspondence, schedules, or background information on the event as well.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); State governments -- United States; United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Philanthropy -- United States; Education; National security -- United States; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Developing countries; Civics; Economics; Economic policy; Business; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Brazil; Civic improvement; Philanthropy; Business enterprises, Foreign; Agriculture -- Latin America; Agriculture; Arts; Art, Primitive; Government agencies; Government policy; Education -- Latin America; Federal government -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; International relations; International economic relations; Latin America; International relations -- United States; Venezuela
- January 5, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Washington, D.C. The Senate. NAR's farewell address to the Senate. Draft, reading copy.
- January 5, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Washington, D.C. 1912 F Street Club. Humorous address by NAR to members of the cabinet at a cabinet dinner. Drafts.
- January 12, 1977; January 13, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  January 12, 1977 -- Washington, D.C. The East Room of the White House, Remarks by NAR on behalf of President Gerald R. Ford at the President's Awards for Distinguished Civil Service. Press release. January 13, 1977 -- Press release announcing staff changes in the Vice President's Press Office.
- January 18, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Transcript of an interview by Dan Rather with Mr. and Mrs. NAR for CBS-TV program, "Who's Who."
- January 29, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Washington, D.C. The Alfalfa Club. Politically humorous speech. Drafts, correspondence and memoranda.
- March 16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  University of California, Davis. Dedication of the Fannie and John Hertz Hall at Lawrence Livermore Laboratory. NAR spoke at the invitation of Edward Teller. NAR speech regarding contribution of applied science to the economy and security of the U.S. Drafts, reading copy, press release, memoranda, correspondence, program and schedule.
- March 18-30, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Trip to the Middle East to promote NAR's Saudi Arabian and American Investment Co. (SARABAM) to facilitate the investment of Saudi Arabian capital reserves. Schedules for Mr. and Mrs. NAR, suggested statements to be made by NAR at various locations, newspaper clipping regarding the trip.
- April 12, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Washington, D.C. Carleton Hotel. Federal City Club's Annual Award for Distinguished Public Service given to NAR. Drafts, reading copy.
- May 9, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. NAR received the first World Covenant of Peace Award by the Synagogue Council of America. NAR speech on peace in Mideast and other foreign policy issues. Drafts, reading copy, press release, newspaper clippings.
- June 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  New York City. Americana Hotel. Alfred P. Sloan Memorial Dinner honoring Betty Ford and Benno Schmidt. Mr. and Mrs. NAR were dinner chairmen. NAR's schedule for June 2. List of people seated on dais. No NAR remarks.
- June 16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. Republican State Committee Dinner. NAR's speech thanking New York State Republican Party and honoring Former President Gerald R. Ford. Drafts, reading copy, press release, NAR's schedule for June 16, letter by NAR saying thanks and farewell to be included in dinner program.
- August 30, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Statement by NAR in response to "New York Magazine" article suggesting that he covered up CIA activities while he was Chairman of the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States. Copy of article and a similar one from the "New York Post." Press release.
- September 13, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Washington, D.C. Senate Finance Committee. Statement by NAR on energy crisis and the need for the Energy Development Corporation. Draft, reading copy, press release.
- October 2, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Pocantico Hills, New York. Guest list and list of nations represented at a reception for United Nations delegates and friends hosted by Mr. and Mrs. NAR. No recorded NAR remarks.
- October 14, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Teheran, Iran. NAR's statement at a reception at the New Museum of Contemporary Arts. Press release.
- October 26, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Albany, New York. NAR received honorary doctorate from the University of the State of New York at the Bicentennial Convocation of the Board of Regents. Program of events, correspondence. No recorded NAR remarks.
- December 16, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Purchase, New York. Meeting of the Westchester Arts Council. NAR was given the WAC's annual award for distinguished service to the arts and then presented a slide show on art. Transcript of NAR's slide show, memoranda, correspondence, and clippings. An audio reel of NAR's talk waS removed from this folder. It is available digitally: AV 9999.
  - NAR Art Speech - Complete Audio, 1977 December 16; ¼ inch audio tape; Sound, 77 minutes (Reel AV 9999)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
    Scope and Contents
    Complete audio recording of the SUNY-Purchase event, including speeches and introductions.
  - NAR Art Speech - Slide Presentation, 1977 December 16; Sound, Color, 29 minutes (AV 9999A)
    Video combining slides of artworks with Nelson Rockefeller's art speech at State University of New York College at Purchase. Note: These are not the actual slides used by NAR for hi spresentation, but rather are images of the art works he is discussing.
    Related Materials
    Complete audio from event - AV 9999.
- March 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Statement by NAR announcing the formation of The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc., an art reproduction company. Press release.
- March 13, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Statement by NAR denying suggestions in "Newsweek" that he asked CIA director William Colby to 'stonewall' the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States, chaired by NAR. Press release.
- March 28, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Statement by NAR to the "Daily News" on his interest in recirculating excess oil monies into productive enterprise. Press release.
- April 14, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  New York City. Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies' Statesman-Humanist Award given to Dr. Alberto Lleras Camargo. NAR in attendance. Clippings and photocopies of photos. No recorded NAR remarks.
- May 8, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Kansas City, Missouri. Harry S. Truman Good Neighbor Award Foundation's Good Neighbor Award presented to NAR at a luncheon. Significant speech on energy and national security. Drafts, reading copy, press release of excerpts, memoranda, correspondence, clippings, schedule of events.
- May 25, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  U.S. House of Representatives gives Distinguished Service Award to NAR. Remarks by NAR. Drafts, reading copy, press release, schedule of events, copy of "Congressional Record" recording the presentation of the award.
- May 26, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  NAR statement and memo answering "tax fraud" stories regarding the sale of his Venezuelan ranches to NAR Farms, Inc., in 1958. Press release.
- May 27, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Pocantico Hills, New York. NAR's 70th birthday party. Guest list, drafts of unattributed remarks honoring NAR, correspondence regarding press coverage, clippings. No recorded NAR remarks.
- June 5, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Albany, New York. Dedication of State University Plaza. Schedule of events. No recorded NAR remarks. Essay on the plaza sent to Hugh Morrow. Clippings of events.
- June 8, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  New York City. Waldorf Astoria Hotel. National Energy Foundation, Energy Achievement Awards Dinner. NAR was guest speaker. Drafts, reading copy, press release, NEF literature used in preparing speech.
- July 13, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for John D. Rockefeller 3rd, who died in an automobile accident July 10. Transcript of eulogy by John D. "Jay" Rockefeller IV. Biographical sketch of JDR 3rd, program for service.
- July 25, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  New York City. Transcript of press conference regarding NAR's arrangement to pay royalties to artists for the right to reproduce certain works of art in his collection. Letters to reporters asking them to attend.
- August 25, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Saratoga, New York. NAR attended Saratoga Performing Arts Center for a concert honoring him and in celebration of his birthday. Clippings of event. Correspondence with NAR's office regarding his attending. No recorded NAR remarks.
- September 7, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Statement on the mailing of The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. mail-order catalogs featuring reproductions of works in NAR's private collection. Press release.
- September 20, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Hamburg, Germany. Meeting of the Atlantic Treaty Association. NAR was keynote speaker. NAR speech on NATO and Soviet expansion. Draft, reading copy, press release, memoranda, clippings, copy of "Congressional Record" wherein NAR's remarks were accepted into the record of the proceedings of the Senate. List of members of Congress who were sent a copy of the speech.
- September 25, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Press release announcing the formation of Nelson Rockefeller Publications, Inc., a company which will produce art books. Photo of Paul Anbinder, Lee Boltin and NAR which was issued with a press release.
- October 3, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  New York City. Meeting of the International Advisory Board of Pan American World Airways. NAR speech on maintaining perspective in international affairs. Draft, reading copy, press release.
- October 3, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  New York City. NAR was Chairman of the New York City Mission Society's Capital Campaign. Taping of NAR's narration of Mission Society promotional slide show. Draft, reading copy.
- October 6, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 36)